ALEX TAYLOR

alex.b.taylor@gmail.com
in linkedin.com/in/alex-b-taylor
www.alexandertaylor.me

SUMMARY

Ph.D. evolutionary biologist turned science communicator. I convey complex scientific ideas in a clear and engaging way, backed up by rigorous fact-checking developed in scientific training. I'm experienced in delivering high-quality science writing that meets organizational needs, on a deadline.

EDUCATION

Ph.D. in Ecology and Evolutionary Biology / 2018 University of Michigan, Ann Arbor, MI

M.S. in Ecology and Evolutionary Biology / 2014 University of Michigan, Ann Arbor, MI

B.S. in Brain, Behavior and Cognitive Science / 2010 University of Michigan, Ann Arbor, MI

SKILLS

Writing, Editing, Interviewing, Teaching, Mentoring, Event Planning, Public Speaking, Social Media Management, Data Presentation, Adobe Illustrator, Microsoft Office Suite, Wordpress, Python, Unix

EXPERIENCE

Vaniam Group, Scientific Communications Team

SENIOR MEDICAL WRITER / AUGUST 2021 - PRESENT

- Prepare and convene scientific advisory boards with key opinion leaders to deliver actionable information to clients in the in the oncology and hematology space
- Deliver relevant and timely insights on the treatment space and disease state in clear, digestible and engaging format

Weber Shandwick, Scientific Communications Team

MANAGER / NOVEMBER 2020 - JULY 2021

SENIOR ASSOCIATE / APRIL 2019 - NOVEMBER 2020

- Created clear and accurate scientific content in a variety of formats, including press releases, Q&A's, infographics, videos, social media posts, websites, articles, presentations, and conference booths
- Created and reviewed content on tight deadlines for a variety of clients, including pharmaceutical companies and patient advocacy groups
- Communicated regularly with multiple clients, worked through feedback to ensure materials met their needs, and helped navigate feedback from internal medical, commercial, legal and regulatory reviewers

Applications in Plant Sciences Journal

CONTRIBUTING WRITER / SEPTEMBER 2017 - FEBRUARY 2020

- · Delivered 500-700 word press releases for monthly peer-reviewed scientific journal on tight deadlines
- Interpreted highly technical, cutting edge botanical studies, interviewed authors and conduct scholarly research to contextualize findings and translate them for a wider audience

TEACHING

GRADUATE STUDENT INSTRUCTOR / SEPTEMBER 2011 - APRIL 2018

- · Taught eight semesters of college classes from 100- to 400-level, on topics in biology
- · Mentored students, wrote reference letters, advised on course and career decisions
- · Consistently earned excellent student evaluations

OUTREACH

THOUGHT AND AWE / DEC 2013 - MAY 2016

- · Founded the blog "Thought and Awe," dedicated to clear science communication with rigorous citation
- · Recruited a team of 10 contributors, collaboratively developed mission, tone, and design guidelines
- · Workshopped stories with contributors, edited blog posts as a team using Wordpress and Google Drive
- · Managed social media presence and developed loyal readership with over 100,000 page views

MICHIGAN SCIENCE WRITERS / APRIL 2016 - JUNE 2018

- Iteratively edited blog posts written by science bloggers with a range of experience.
- Worked with rotating teams of editors to address clarity, jargon, structure, and narrative aspects of blog posts written by graduate students translating their research for a wider audience

SCHOLARLY ARTICLES

- Mower, J. P., Ma, P. F., Grewe, F., Taylor, A.B, Michael, T. P., VanBuren, R., & Qiu, Y. L. (2019). Lycophyte
 plastid genomics: extreme variation in GC, gene and intron content and multiple inversions between a direct
 and inverted orientation of the rRNA repeat. New Phytologist, 222(2), 1061-1075.
- Taylor, A.B. & Qiu, Y.L. (2017). Evolutionary history of subtilases in land plants and their involvement in symbiotic interactions. *Molecular Plant-Microbe Interactions*, 30(6), 489-501.
- King, A. P., Muzik, M., Hamilton, L., Taylor, A. B., Rosenblum, K. L., & Liberzon, I. (2016). Dopamine receptor gene DRD4 7-repeat allele X maternal sensitivity interaction on child externalizing behavior problems: independent replication of effects at 18 months. *PloS one*, 11(8), e0160473.
- Qiu, Y.L., Taylor, A.B., & McManus, H.A. (2012). Evolution of the life cycle in land plants. Journal of Systematics and Evolution, 50(3), 171-194.